{"tossups": [{"question": "English adventurer Thomas Stuckley died fighting for this country. In this country's War of Succession, the Prior of Crato was defeated at the Battle of Alcantara. This country defended its independence at the Battle of Aljubarrota. This country's King Sebastian was killed during the Battle of Alcacer Quibir. The minister Marquis de (*) Pombal helped model this country's capital. This country, which originally conquered Ceuta and Melila from Morocco, developed the caravel which enabled it to conquer Macau, Angola, and Mozambique. Henry the Navigator was from, for 10 points, what country whose capital is Lisbon", "answer": "Portugal", "subcategory": "European History", "category": "History"}, {"question": "During this war, one character begins a \"sexless\" relationship with the socialist Willi at the Mashopi hotel. A soldier in this war has his boots taken and is forced to march in wooden clogs, leading to his death from gangrene. In the aftermath of this war, a character studying optometry is visited in a mental hospital by Valencia Merble, with whom he discusses the novels of an obscure science-fiction author. After discovering that (*) Orr has escaped this war, one character escapes to Sweden; that character was earlier stabbed by Nately's whore. During this war, the schoolteacher Edgar Derby is shot for \"looting\" a teapot. A food-shipping cartel is run by Milo Minderbinder during this war, during which Billy Pilgrim is kept in Slaughterhouse-Five. For 10 points, name this war, the setting of Catch-22.", "answer": "World War II [or WW2]", "subcategory": "Long Fiction", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "Arm DDT is used to perform this process. Bunyan helps people perform this process by creating JSON files. In an April Fools prank, one form of this process was referenced by a feature called QuackOverflow; that process involves talking to an inanimate rubber duck. This process can involve stepping into or over (*) breakpoints. People performing this process may examine the call stack to find the line number where a syntax error may have occurred. The term for this process was coined when Grace Hopper removed a moth from the Mark II computer. For 10 points, name this process of removing mistakes from a computer program.", "answer": "debugging [accept descriptions like removing bugs or finding bugs or removing errors or finding errors in code or error trapping; accept rubber duck debugging; prompt on logging or printing errors or bugs]", "subcategory": "Other Science", "category": "Science"}, {"question": "Near the beginning of this opera, one character speaks of an attempt to poison an Englishman's parrot with parsley; that character enters after two others cry \"Down with the author!\" In this opera, two characters kiss a ribbon and a pink bonnet as they think of their loves. One character in this opera blows out a candle and pockets a lost key to spend more time with another, leading him to sing the aria (*) \"Che gelida manina.\" One character in this opera abandons her lover Alcindoro and sings a namesake waltz to regain Marcello's affection; that character is Musetta. At the end of this opera, Rodolfo begins to cry when Mimi dies from tuberculosis. This opera inspired the musical Rent. For 10 points, name this opera set in Paris' Latin Quarter, by Giacomo Puccini.", "answer": "La Boh\u00e8me", "subcategory": "Other Fine Arts", "category": "Fine Arts"}, {"question": "Gregory Stanton described these events as having \"symbolization\" as one of their ten stages. Samantha Power criticized the American response to these events in A Problem From Hell. Rom\u00e9o Dallaire's book Shake Hands with the Devil analyzes the response to one of these events. A convention that aimed to prevent these events was pushed by (*) Raphael Lemkin, who named these events. An analyst who studied these events divided them into stages like \"classification,\" \"discrimination,\" and \"dehumanization,\" before ending in \"extermination\" and \"denial.\" That work was influenced by one of these in Rwanda against the Tutsi. For 10 points, name these mass killings of a targeted group of people, such as the Holocaust.", "answer": "genocides", "subcategory": "Social Science", "category": "Social Science"}, {"question": "In this play, a \"wasting disease of the frontal lobes\" and a \"wonder drug\" are given as definitions of ABMAPHID by one character who distrusts biologists because they are \"rearranging our genes.\" A line from A Streetcar Named Desire is quoted by one character in this play when he appears with snapdragons. One character in this play recites the Libera Me while another speaks of a character who died when he (*) swerved to avoid a porcupine; that character is one couple's imaginary son. During this play's second act, \"Walpurgisnacht,\" two couples play games like \"get the guest.\" This play ends with one character repeating \"I... am...\" in response to the title question. For 10 points, name this play centering on the dysfunctional couple George and Martha, by Edward Albee.", "answer": "Who's Afraid of Virginia Woolf?", "subcategory": "Drama", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "A problem about this statement's triviality was solved by the Maccone-Pati relation. Earle Kennard noted that the canonical commutation relation implied this statement, since one form of this statement contains a one over 2i term and holds for any two conjugate variables. This statement can be explained by imagining a (*) microscope observing an electron and therefore changing its movement. In this statement, the product of two standard deviations, such as energy and time, must be greater than or equal to h-bar divided by 2. For 10 points, name this statement which states that a position and momentum cannot both be precisely known, named for a German physicist.", "answer": "Heisenberg uncertainty principle [accept either underlined part; accept \"equation\" or \"relation\" in place of principle]", "subcategory": "Physics", "category": "Science"}, {"question": "The final movement of this work opens with the maestoso melody [read slowly] whole notes E-flat, F, half note G, quarter notes E flat-G, half notes D-G, played over block chords. An oft-repeated melody in this work opens with the notes [read slowly] G-F-B flat-C-F-D and is first presented in 5/4-6/4 mixed meter. A \"Dance of Chickens in their Shells\" in this work is followed by a section whose opening crescendo depicts the approach of an oxcart, (*) \"Bydlo.\" Maurice Ravel's orchestration of this programmatic work uses an alto saxophone to depict a troubadour outside an \"Old Castle.\" A \"Promenade\" theme is varied throughout this piano suite. Viktor Hartmann's paintings inspired, for 10 points, what suite by Modest Mussorgsky?", "answer": "Pictures at an Exhibition", "subcategory": "Auditory Fine Arts", "category": "Fine Arts"}, {"question": "The mother of one figure in this religion had visions of the rising sun, a full moon, and a great fire. Right perception, right knowledge, and right faith are the \"three jewels\" of this religion. This religion believes that space, time, and the principle of motion are among the six eternal substances of the universe, which is made up of three worlds called lokas. Rishabhanatha and (*) Mahavira are two important figures in this religion.Two sects of this religion are the Digambara and \u015av\u0113t\u0101mbara, or \"sky clad\" and \"white clad.\" 24 spiritual teachers called tirthankaras, are central to this religion. For 10 points, name this religion, which emerged alongside Buddhism in ancient India.", "answer": "Jainism", "subcategory": "Religion", "category": "Religion"}, {"question": "A leader of this country adopted a policy translated as \"beans and bullets\" to gain support for his government, which was opposed by the Guerrilla Army of the Poor, or the EGP. A leader of this country was targeted by Operation WASHTUB before being replaced by Carlos Castillo Armas. Rigoberta Menchu, an activist from this country, won the Nobel Peace Prize for supporting the (*) K'ich'e people here. A CIA-backed 1954 coup in this country, Operation PBSUCCESS, deposed its leader Jacobo Arbenz and made this country a \"banana republic\" dominated by the United Fruit Company. Tikal is one of many Mayan ruins in this country. For 10 points, name this country which borders Belize and Mexico", "answer": "Republic of Guatemala", "subcategory": "World History", "category": "History"}, {"question": "This author called the title object of one poem a \"lovely seneschal\" and an \"exquisite grotesque\"; that object \"has watched me / through the shifting gloom.\" Another poem by this author opens by describing Charles Thomas Wooldridge with the line \"He did not wear his scarlet coat.\" This poet wrote \"some do it with a bitter look, some with a flattering word\" in a poem ending \"the (*) brave man does it with a kiss, the coward with a sword.\" This author declared \"Each man kills the thing he loves\" in a poem named for the place where he was imprisoned for homosexuality. For 10 points, name this Irish poet of \"The Ballad of Reading Gaol\" who also wrote The Picture of Dorian Gray.", "answer": "Oscar Wilde", "subcategory": "Poetry", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "It's not carbon or hydrogen, but the \"cyclohexa\" allotrope of this element exists in a chair conformation. An ion of this element is responsible for the deep blue color of lapis lazuli. An anion containing this element and oxygen is titrated against iodine in iodometry. This element is extracted by pumping superheated water into the ground in the (*) Frasch process. A diprotic acid of this element can be produced using a vanadium catalyst in the contact process. This element is added to rubber in vulcanization. This element is bonded to hydrogen in thiols. For 10 points, name this element responsible for the rotten smell of eggs with atomic number 16.", "answer": "sulfur [or S]", "subcategory": "Chemistry", "category": "Science"}, {"question": "In one Japanese fairy tale, Urashima Taro saves the daughter of a deity of this domain from children, and receives a box which prevents him from aging as a reward. The goddess R\u00e1n is married to a deity of this domain who has 9 daughters. That god of this domain converses with Bragi in the Skaldskaparmal. This domain of (*) Aegir was home to a god who married the nymph Amphitrite and fathered Triton. Oddysseus incurs the wrath of that god after blinding that god's son, Polyphemus. That god also created horses and caused earthquakes with his trident. For 10 points, name this aquatic domain of Posiedon.", "answer": "the ocean [or the sea]", "subcategory": "Mythology", "category": "Mythology"}, {"question": "Daniel Burnham's plan to redesign this city called for a large urban park by its Twin Peaks and adding an Athenaeum. Lotta's Fountain served as a meeting place for residents of this city after a natural disaster. Mayor Eugene Schmitz led the dynamiting of much of this city. Records destroyed in this city helped many people bring over (*) \"paper children.\" This city developed from the town of Yerba Buena as well as a military presidio. Large fires in this city devastated its Nob Hill district. A natural disaster in this city provided land to build Fisherman's Wharf and destroyed much of its historic Chinatown. For 10 points, name this Northern California city devastated by a 1906 earthquake.", "answer": "San Francisco", "subcategory": "American History", "category": "History"}, {"question": "A song written by this author contrasts a certain character's \"red thoughts\" with his white teeth. Two men hunting in a \"forest of mixed growth\" in the Carpathians are caught under a fallen beech tree in a story by this author; those men are the mortal enemies Znaeym and Gradwitz. Because he believes them to be \"dashing and not very respectable,\" one character of this author decides that his Houdan hen is an anabaptist. In that story by this author, (*) Conradin butters a piece of toast while Mrs. de Ropp is killed by the title polecat. A story by this author ends by noting that Vera Sappleton's \"specialty\" is \"romance at short notice.\" For 10 points, name this author of \"Sredni Vashtar\" and \"The Open Window.\"", "answer": "Saki [or H. H. Munro]", "subcategory": "Short Fiction", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "This compound is the substrate of a manganese containing metalloenzyme which cycles through the S0 to the S4 states. During the Krebs cycle, this compound is removed and then added in the conversion of citrate to isocitrate. Plants can uptake this compound through either the symplastic or apoplastic route, but it must pass through the (*) Casparian strip. The hormone ADH signals for reabsorption of this compound. Aquaporins facilitate the transport of this compound across a cell membrane. This compound is transported from the roots to the leaves by the xylem. For 10 points, name this compound which makes up most of the volume of the cytosol.", "answer": "water [or H2O]", "subcategory": "Biology", "category": "Science"}, {"question": "In a painting titled for an object of this color, the artist and his daughter Ida are depicted as tiny figures playing among some trees; in that painting, the artist's wife Bella Rosenfeld looks down and wears a titular collar of this color. Another painting titled for this color features a man with outstretched hands that wears a green robe, as well as soldiers with flags destroying houses on its left. A (*) synagogue is depicted burning on the right of a painting titled for this color in which a menorah is depicted at the feet of Jesus, who is shown as a Jewish martyr. This color titles a Marc Chagall \"Crucifixion.\"  This color is \"beaten\" with the Red Wedge in a Soviet propaganda poster. For 10 points, name this color used to paint snow.", "answer": "white [accept Bella with White Collar; accept White Crucifixion; accept Beat the Whites with the Red Edge]", "subcategory": "Visual Fine Arts", "category": "Fine Arts"}], "bonuses": [{"leadin": "Jean Chardin published travelogues about this empire describing making jewelry in it. People from this empire gained access to religious sites in the Peace of Amasya. This empire described its capital as \"half the world\" in an alliterative saying. The philosopher Mulla Sadra worked under this empire. The last ruler of this dynasty was deposed by Nadir, who had put him on the throne. Military organizations that supported this empire were named for their (*) red caps; those were the Qizilbash. Because of a lack of advanced weapons, this empire lost the Battle of Chaldiran. Abbas the Great made Isfahan the capital of this empire. Ismail I founded this empire and led it to be Twelver Shia. For 10 points, name this Persian empire that repeatedly fought the Ottomans ANSWER: Safavid Empire <Dartley, World History> <ed. McAvoy-Bickford>  A theorem named for this mathematician and Edouard Goursat gives criteria under which the integral of a complex-valued function is zero. For 10 points each:", "parts": ["Name this French mathematician. An inequality that states that the dot product of two vectors is less than or equal to the product of their magnitudes is named for this mathematician and Hermann Schwarz.", "The Cauchy-Goursat theorem applies only to analytic functions, which have the complex type of this property. It is possible to take the derivative of a function with this property.", "The theorem only holds if the region enclosed by the curve being integrated over has the \"simple\" form of this property, which is stronger than its \"path\" form. Euler's formula only holds for planar graphs that have this property."], "answers": ["Safavid Empire", "Augustin-Louis Cauchy", "differentiability [accept word forms like differentiable]", "connectedness [accept simply-connected or path-connected or k-connected, I guess]"], "subcategory": "World History", "category": "History"}, {"leadin": "26 or so people have drowned in this state's Round Valley Reservoir, which was then labeled this state's Bermuda Triangle. The Kirkwood-Cohansey aquifer supplies water to much of this state. Perth Amboy and Asbury Park are two of the many beach towns on this state's coast. This state's northeast contains numerous palisades by a river near (*) Fort Lee. This state's south is dominated by Cape May. The Raritan river runs through the center of this state, where the Passaic and Hackensack rivers also meet. This state contains large pine barrens along the Garden State Parkway. The Delaware River forms most of the western border of this state. For 10 points, name this state home to Trenton and Newark ANSWER: New Jersey<Dartley, Geography> <ed. McAvoy-Bickford>  After one character in this play warns Alexandra that she will have to marry her cousin Leo, she is brutally slapped across the face by her husband. For 10 points each:", "parts": ["Name this play. In this play, one character withholds her ailing husband's medication and blackmails her brothers Oscar and Benjamin over stolen railroad bonds to get a larger share in a cotton mill.", "This author wrote The Little Foxes. Karen and Martha are accused of having a lesbian affair in this author's play The Children's Hour.", "Hellman's Watch On The Rhine ends with the death of a Romanian Nazi collaborator with this title, Teck de Brancovis. A Transylvanian character with this title is the subject of Bram Stoker's Dracula."], "answers": ["New Jersey", "The Little Foxes", "Lillian Hellman", "count [accept Count Teck de Brancovis or Count Dracula]"], "subcategory": "Geography", "category": "Geography"}, {"leadin": "In 2011, Tom Brady told an alumni of this university that he was \"watching over\" two of his college teammates. While at this school, one person threw a stolen laptop out a dorm window and later transferred to Blinn College. Other former players from this university who had legal troubles include Janoris Jenkins and Aaron Hernandez. A quarterback from this university had (*) John 3:16 written on eye black and famously knelt in prayer before games. Steve Spurrier won a Heisman at this university and later coached at it. A quarterback from this university became a minor league player for the New York Mets before returning to this university's state in 2021 to play for the Jacksonville Jaguars. For 10 points, Tim Tebow attended what university in Gainesville whose mascot is the Gators ANSWER: University of Florida [accept UF]<Tong, Pop Culture/Sports> <ed. McAvoy-Bickford>  One ruler of this house signed the Treaty of Trausnitz with Frederick the Fair, in which he was declared sole Holy Roman Emperor; that didn't stop Pope John XXII from excommunicating him, though. For 10 points each.", "parts": ["Name this house, of which Emperor Louis IV was a member. Members of this house, like the \"Mad King\" Ludwig II, ruled Bavaria.", "Ludwig II of Bavaria is most famous for constructing one of these fortified buildings named Neuschwanstein.", "A Wittelsbach ruler of Bohemia with this name was nicknamed \"The Winter King\" due to the short length of his reign. An earlier emperor with this name was defeated by the Lombard League at the Battle of Legnano."], "answers": ["University of Florida [accept UF]", "House of Wittelsbach", "castles [accept Neuschwanstein castle]", "Frederick [accept Frederick V or Frederick the Winter King; accept Frederick Barbarossa or Frederick I]"], "subcategory": "Trash", "category": "Trash"}]}